The Seymour Fisher PhD Papers
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The Seymour Fisher PhD Papers
1958-1996
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Fisher, Seymour
1.25 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of Seymour Fisher, who was a Professor of Psychiatry and Behavioral Science, and head of the psychology research program at SUNY Upstate Medical University. The highlights of this collection are his correspondence with colleagues and research data from his Rorschach ink blot tests. This collection has six series: Administrative and Teaching Records, Correspondence, Printed Materials, Research, Writings by Dr. Fisher, and Writings by Others.
FIC2019.0021.
Biographical Note
Seymour Fisher (1922-1996) was born on May 13, 1922 in Baltimore, MD. He earned his PhD in Psychology in 1948 at the University of Chicago. In 1961 he became a professor at SUNY Health Science Center in Syracuse, NY (now named SUNY Upstate Medical University) and taught in the College of Medicine for 34 years. He was a professor in the Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Science, and headed the psychology research program. While at SUNY Upstate Medical University he conducted several research studies on nurses with Rorschach ink blot tests. His research also included topics of psychology, pharmacology, body image, Freudian analysis, humor, and female sexuality; the last of which drew a large general audience. His research into psychoactive drugs scrutinized drug companies that released drugs (like anti-depressants) onto the market before having put them through rigorous, scientific testing. He also worked with colleagues around the country, including Dr. Sidney E. Cleveland, David Mendell, and Dr. Roger P. Greenberg (a colleague in Syracuse). Dr. Fisher wrote several books (19 in total published). He also published about 200 research articles.
His wife, Dr. Rhoda Fisher, was a clinical psychologist and had a private practice in child psychology in Manlius, NY. She and Seymour researched the psychology of humor and wrote at least two books together (Pretend the World is Funny and Forever: A Psychological Analysis of Comedians, Clowns, and Actors, 1982; and The Psychology of Adaptation to Absurdity: Tactics of Make-Believe, 1993). Their work put them into contact with comedians like Kaye Ballard, Sid Caesar, and Jackie Mason.
Dr. Fisher died of a heart attack on December 5, 1996 at the age of 74. He was living in Manlius, NY at the time.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the professional activities of Seymour Fisher during his employment at SUNY Upstate Medical University. It also includes personal correspondence, photo-copied journal articles on topics of research, articles and cartoon clippings, manuscripts, conference booklets, administrative documents, publishing documents, research information from some of his Rorschach ink blot tests, and other material. Items document professional and personal relationships with colleagues, the process of researching and publishing his writing, administrative information about courses and faculty at SUNY Health Science Center/SUNY Upstate Medical University, and raw research data. Topics include body image, psychology, pharmacology, sexuality, and humor. Medium is paper, including newsprint, book paper, and coated paper for printed publications; lined loose-leaf, graph paper, copy paper, and transfer paper. Format is mostly letter-size or smaller, typed or handwritten.
There are six series in this collection.
Administrative and Teaching Records: this series contains employment-related records, including a job evaluation form for Dr. Fisher, a faculty candidate's CV, photocopies of other's published material, course notes, and a memo. 1991-1996, undated.
Correspondence: this series contains personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher. Primary contact of correspondence is Dr. Sidney Cleveland. 1980-1996.
Printed Materials: this series contains a subject file with biographical information and obituaries on Dr. Fisher. It also contains a book publishing agreement, conference proceedings from the First Annual Conference on Trauma, Loss and Dissociation: The Foundations of 21st Century Traumatology (02/16/1995-02/20/1995), clippings, and a proof copy of Body Image and Personality, by Seymour Fisher and Sidney E. Cleveland. 1958-1995.
Research: this series contains raw research data, test results, logs, and notes, primarily from projects labeled "Research Cruise: Future Topics", "Blots: Project 36: Nurses", and "Proj 143: Orig: Blots". 1983-1984, undated.
Writings by Dr. Fisher: this series contains reviews, published writings, and unpublished writings by Dr. Fisher. 1959-1995.
Writings by Others: this series contains manuscripts from Dr. Dan Egli, Dr. Marc Runco, Dr. Roland Moses, Dr. Richard Karmel, and Dr. Jill Reardon; as well as photocopied books and articles. 1994, undated.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Seymour Fisher PhD Papers have been arranged into six series by material type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Cleveland, Sidney E. (Sidney Earl), 1919-; Fisher, Rhoda L. (Rhoda Lee), 1924-; Fisher, Seymour; Greenberg, Roger P.; Mendell, David; Upstate Medical University (N.Y.); Body image; Freudian Theory; Humor; Medical education; Pharmacology; Psychiatry; Psychology; Rorschach Test; Sexuality; Administrative records; Agreements; Clippings (information artifacts); Conference proceedings; Correspondence; Manuscripts (documents); Printed materials (object genre); Proofs (printed matter); Research (documents); Reviews (documents); Writings (documents)
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Administrative and Teaching Records
  - Employment-related records., 1991; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies of other’s published material., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Course notes and a memo., 1996; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence
  - Personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher., 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher., 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher., 1980-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher., 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal and professional correspondence to and from Dr. Fisher., 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Printed Materials
  - Subject file, biographical information and obituaries on Dr. Fisher. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publishing agreement, conference proceedings., 1992; 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings of cartoons and articles by others., 1962-1978; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Proof copy., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Research
  - “Research Cruise: Future Topics”., undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “Blots: Project 36: Nurses”., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Computer Output Log”., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “Proj 143: Orig: Blots”., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings by Dr. Fisher
  - Published and unpublished writings by Dr. Fisher., 1959-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Writings by Others
  - Manuscripts by others., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied books and articles., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied books and articles., undated (Box 3, Folder 4)